Guide to the Theon H. Durnford Papers 1913-1924
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Theon H. Durnford papers
1913-1924
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 750
Durnford, Theon H., 1877-1972
1.0 linear feet
This collection contains letters from customers throughout Montana and nearby states ordering fruit from Theon H. Durnford in Lolo, Montana, 1913-1924 and Durnford's receipts and statements from Hughes Mercantile in Lolo between 1917 and 1919.
Biographical Note
Theon H. Durnford was born on September 10, 1877 in Salt Lake City, Utah. In 1910 he moved from Idaho to Lolo, Montana, and began farming. From 1913 to at least 1924 Durnford operated a fruit farm in Lolo where he grew apples, cherries, plums, and a variety of other fruits. Durnford sold his fruit to customers throughout Montana and as far away as Pierre, South Dakota. In addition, he sold eggs to a Hughes Mercantile of Lolo, Montana, in exchange for goods and services. Durnford lived in Lolo until he moved to Missoula, Montana, in 1970. He died in Missoula on July 3, 1972.
This collection contains letters from customers throughout Montana and nearby states ordering fruit from Theon H. Durnford in Lolo, Montana, 1913-1924, with the bulk from 1918, and Durnford's receipts and statements from Hughes Mercantile of Lolo, Montana, from 1917-1919.The bulk of the letters are orders for Theon H. Dunford’s fruit but a few letters also contain personal, cultural, and social information on topics including the influenza epidemic, the scarcity of workers during the First World War, and oil drilling. The letters also offer information about the varieties of fruit Durnford grew, how these fruits were shipped, how customers chose to use the products, and how a small agricultural business functioned at the time. Durnford shipped his fruit both to individual customers and retail distributors. Many of his customers were in Big Timber, Three Forks, Toston, and Townsend, Montana.
The receipts and invoices from Hughes Mercantile record Durnford's sale of eggs to the store in exchange for everything from laundry to canned peas and chicken feed.
This collection is divided into two series:
Series I: Business Correspondence, 0.75 linear feet, 1913-1924
Series II: Receipts and Statements, 0.25 linear feet, 1917-1919
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The chain of ownership of this collection is unknown.
This collection was donated to the Archives by the Historical Museum at Fort Missoula in 1998.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Hughes Mercantile (Lolo, Mont.)
Fruit--Transportation--Montana--Lolo; Fruit-culture--Montana--Lolo; General stores--Montana--Lolo; Influenza Epidemic, 1918-1919--Montana; Oil well drilling--Montana; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects--Montana
Business records--Montana--Lolo
Montana; Agriculture
Fruit growers--Montana--Lolo
- Business Correspondence, 1913-1924; Series I; 0.75 linear feet
  - Business correspondence, 1913 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Business correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Business correspondence, 1916 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Business correspondence, 1917 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Business correspondence, January-July 1918 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Business correspondence, August-Sepetember 1918 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Business correspondence, October 1918 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Business correspondence, November-December 1918 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Business correspondence, 1919-August 1923 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Business correspondence, September 1923-1924 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Business correspondence, undated (Box-folder 2/4)
- Receipts and Statements, 1917-1919; Series II; 0.25 linear feet
  Receipts and statements for items bought and sold at Hughes Mercantile in Lolo, Montana.
  - Receipts and statements, 1917 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Receipts and satetments, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2/4)